# 哈喽 大家好 现在快要到端午节了
Hello, everyone. It's almost the Dragon Boat Festival.
# 我们今天弄一点粽子
We want to try making some Zongzi
# 这个粽子（米）我四伯爷已经泡了两三个小时了嘎
Uncle has soaked this glutinous rice for about 2 to 3 hours
# 两三个小时是有的
At least 2 to 3 hours
# 这里是4斤糯米
Here we have 4 Jin (2kg) glutinous rice,
# 然后一斤这个
and 1 Jin (0.5kg)
# 饭米饭米
white rice.
# 那我们包啥子安 有蛋黄有那个香肠腊肉
What do we have for the filling? We have duck egg yolk, sausage and salted pork.
# 就包香肠腊肉的好吃点
I like sausage and salted pork
# 包香肠腊肉的啊
Sausage and salted pork?
# 嗯 包蛋的麻烦得很 就包那个简单点的
Yes. Egg yolk is a mess to deal with. Let's go with the easier ones.
# 我们这个蛋黄老人家胆固醇比较高
Egg yolk is rich in cholesterol, which is not so healthy for the senior,
# 所以就
so let's...
# 反正我四伯爷也喜欢吃肉嘛就包香肠腊肉就行了
Anyway, since uncle likes meat, we will go with sausage and salted pork.
# 然后现在还差个粽叶
Now we need the leaves to wrap with
# 走嘛 我们去摘粽叶
Let's go pick some
# 走嘛 就到我们背后去摘
Let's go. Just around the corner.
# 我那儿有我栽的笋竹的竹叶很大片一个
Those bamboo I've planted have really large leaves
# 好 要得
Good. That's great.
# 就摘点来包
Go pick some
# 好
OK
# 就是那个是不
Is it over there?
# 诶呀
Aiyah
# 那里的大片点
(Leaves) over there are larger
# 哦
Oh
# 这里好多嘛你看
Look at those many large leaves
# 好
Good
# 够了
That's enough
# 可以了
Good enough
# 诶呀
Aiyah
# 我们这里漫山遍野都是包粽子的材料
We have everything we need to make Zongzi here
# 这个粽叶就这么大了
These leaves are not so wide
# 这片还好 这片
This piece is better. This one.
# 诶 这片颜色好看
Ei. It has a nice color.
# 嗯
Yes
# 走嘛
Let's go
# 到处都是
(Bamboo leaves) are everywhere
# 现在我们这个粽叶就已经摘回来了
Now we have the bamboo leaves
# 但是这个粽叶的话
But we can't
# 摘回来不能直接用来包
use them directly
# 大家可以看一下这个上面
You can see under the leaves there are
# 油虫卵
aphid larvae.
# 很多虫卵嘎
Many larvae
# 这个上面有虫卵 所以我们要烧开水把这个放到开水里面去煮一下
There are insect larvae. So we must boil the leaves
# 煮完了之后再洗干净了再用来包
and wash thoroughly before using.
# 这样更安全嘎
It's safer this way
# 通过高温的（煮）这个（虫卵）就遭了撒
(Boiling under) high temperature can kill them (larvae)
# 就把它烫死了撒
Can kill them
# 要得 我拿得蒸锅里去煮哈
Good. I'll boil them and later
# 煮了再洗干净了
wash thoroughly.
# 煮了来洗干净来包
Boil and wash
# 好了这个粽叶我们已经煮好了
OK. Now the leaves are boiled
# 煮完了之后又洗干净了 现在先放一边
and cleaned. We leave them aside for now.
# 我切点香肠跟腊肉
Let me prepare the sausage and salted pork
# 这个香肠的话我们就切颗粒 切大一点的颗粒
We can cut sausage into dice. Large dice.
# 大点的颗粒吃起要上口点
Larger dice are more chewy
# 哦喔
Yes
# 先把它对半切这种条 然后再切成长粒
First cut lengthwise into slim pieces and then into chunks
# 腊肉的话我们就稍微切小一点
We can cut salted pork into small pieces
# 因为这个腊肉切大了咬不动
because it's difficult to chew.
# 我切成片片嘛这个嘎
I'm going to cut into slices
# 可以按
Sure
# 切成厚片就可以
This thickness should be fine
# 你切这么大坨包起粽子好大个
We'll definitely be making large Zongzi since those pieces are so large
# 好现在我们来和这个米
Now we mix the two kinds of rice
# 调一下味简单的
and add some flavor.
# 我们这个米的话可以不用搞得太复杂放点酱油就行了
We keep it simple and only add some soy sauce
# 调个底味
to make a base flavor.
# 大概倒个三四两酱油就可以了
About 3 or 4 Liang (150-200g) soy sauce
# 然后再放一点点老抽调下这个颜色
Then a little bit of dark soy sauce to add some color
# 好 可以了
Good enough
# 我们的香肠和腊肉都比较咸 所以就不加盐了就加这个就够了
Sausage and salted pork are salty enough so we leave out the salt
# 加点酱油加点老抽有点颜色有点底味就可以了
These two sauces are enough for the flavor and color
# 我这个粽子啊因为做的比较少
I've rarely made any Zongzi,
# 我都是现跟前辈请教怎么包
so I just learned how to make them from experienced seniors right before this.
# 今天就包一个最简单的四角粽
Today we will make the easiest four-corner Zongzi
# 粽子有三角 有圆角 有四角
Zongzi can come with three corners, round corners or four corners
# 四角是最简单的
Four-corner Zongzi is the easiest to make
# 好 现在粽叶我们已经弄好了
Good. Now we have the bamboo leaves,
# 米也弄好了
rice and
# 香肠腊肉也好了 我们来包一下
meat ready, let's try making one.
# 第一次尝试来包啊 包得不好
This is my first time making Zongzi. It may not turn out good.
# 两头给它剪掉
Scissor both sides
# 然后这个粽叶背靠背给它靠起来
and attach the underside of both leaves.
# 然后对折一下
Then fold in half
# 对折过来之后这边给它这样子折一下
and seal one side by folding slightly inward.
# 折起来了这边就可以打开
Now we can open from the other side
# 打开米就不会掉下去
without rice falling through once added.
# 好 现在我们放点米
Good. Now we add rice.
# 放点糯米
Some glutinous rice,
# 再放点这个香肠和腊肉
some sausage and salted pork,
# 再放点糯米
and then more glutinous rice.
# 包小一点 反正我们这个粽叶也不大
We'll make a small Zongzi since the leaves are not so big
# 然后这样子给它对折一下
Then fold like this
# 对折的时候两边手就给它捏紧
while holding tight on both sides of the opening.
# 捏一下
Squeeze tightly
# 捏下了之后这两边给它弄下去
Cover the opening on both sides
# 好
Nice
# 然后再用这个线给它缠起来
Now we wrap the string around,
# 从头缠到尾
from head to tail.
# 好 我们这个粽子小是小了点
OK. Our Zongzi is rather small
# 嗯 虽然说不是很漂亮 但是都是自己做的嘛吃起来更放心
and less appealing but it's safer since everything passes our hands and inspection. (...but it's the effort that matters在想这样翻，怕外国人理解不了“为什么别人做就不放心”，不过这算意译了)
# 来嘛 继续
Come. Let's continue.
# 我包的你看越来越更好看了
See? I'm becoming better at this.
# 你越来越整的好撒 说明你做好了撒
Better means you are trying your best
# 又成一个
Another one
# 可以
Nice
# 哈哈哈
Hahaha
(Uncle imitating) Hahaha
# 哈哈哈
(Everyone) Hahaha
# 四伯爷的模仿好像哦 模仿还多像
That was a really impressive imitation, uncle. Really lively.
# 包得还可以 剪了
Nice wrapping. Cut here.
# 好了 经过半个小时的包啊 他们都不包了
OK. After half an hour of work, they both quit.
# 现在只留我跟伯娘两个人在这里
Now only aunt and I are left
# 这个肉抓进去
Get those meat in
# 嗯
En
# 捏住它
Squeeze it
# 这个做这个白案 做这个粑粑很多学问
(Uncle from afar) To be a "Bai An" chef and good at making dough food is not easy
# 好 可以了现在
Good. Good enough.
# 我就一个人慢慢包了 不等他们了
I'll keep on going. There's no need to wait for them.
# 把须须剪了的
You should cut those dangling strings
# 须须啊
Those strings?
# 嗯
En
# 剪不剪都可以
Either way is fine
# 好了 我们这个粽子大的大小的小
OK. Now we have various size Zongzi
# 总之我觉得前面包的不怎么样 后面包的还可以
I think the last few I made was much better than the first ones
# 大家可以看一下这个是我包的
You can see this one is from me
# 这是我包的
I made this
# 这个是哪个包的哦
Who made this one?
# 漆二娃包的
Qi Erwa
# 诶呀
Aiyah
# 好了这次我们的直接用来蒸
Good. Now we steam.
# 反正做厨子这一行嘛
Although chef has two kinds,
# 白案跟红案的话 虽然说白案不怎么熟可以学着来做一下
"Bai An" and "Hong An", one can still try learning and doing things from the other side.
# 嘎四伯爷
Right, uncle?
# 可以安 可以尝试哈撒
Indeed. Try doing unfamiliar things.
# 反正自己吃的没那么讲究
They are not for sale. It's fine they don't look as good.
# 好 现在我们就把它放下去蒸一下
OK. Now we steam.
# 那个（线）对这那个（线）
Align (the two seams)
# 这样子的啊
Like this?
# 对对对
Yes. Good.
# 好 现在我们就要蒸3个小时
OK. Now we wait 3 hours.
# 好了我们这个已经差不多了
OK. Now it's good enough
# 我先关火嘛
Let me cut the gas first
# 我们这个粽子已经蒸了有三四个小时了
It has been steamed for 3 to 4 hours
# 这个水都烧干了2次了
We've added water twice after it dried out
# 因为没有包得很紧所以就蒸
We choose to steam because the wrappings are not tight,
# 煮的话怕全部漏出来
and fillings might come out if we chose to boil.
# 哇噻
Wow!
# 你闻哈看 都闻到酒米的那个香味了
Have a smell. The aroma of glutinous rice.
# 嗯
En
# 是不
Smelt it?
# 这个生蒸的这个肯定是安逸点了
Steamed (Zongzi) is definitely better
# 诶呀 好香哦
Aiyah. Smells so good.
# 我还选得到我包的
I can see which one I made
# 你包的这个 这个就是你包的
You made this one?
# 那不是咋子
Of course
# 没有包紧这个
Not very tightly wrapped
# 拿这个整得盘子头
Put this in a pan
# 看到很烫
Careful. Very hot.
# 很烫啊先吃一个小的嘛
Hot? Choose smaller ones then.
# 我解开来冷一哈都
I'll open it up and let it cool
# 吃撒
Go on.
# 冷一哈安
Let it cool first
# 好了的 你看嘛这
They are well cooked. Here, see?
# 好了的 蒸了这么久还没好
Of course. They've been steamed for so long.
# 嗯 你看我包的有坨香肠 有坨腊肉
En. You see the one I made has one piece of sausage and one piece of salted pork.
# 你硬是吃你的那个啊
You are eating the one you made? (这句感觉意思有点把捏不到位)
# 嗯
En
# 他认到自己包的那个吃
He recognizes that one
# 嗯
En
# 可以啊
Good?
# 可以 好香哦
Nice. Very delicious.
# 嗯
En
# 颜色还可以
The color is just right
# 可以
Good
# 唯一的没整到位就是不是很糯
The only thing is the rice isn't soft enough
# 泡时间短了噶
It need more time soaking
# 哦 泡时间短了
Oh. Longer time soaking.
# 总结一下我们这个粽子
A summary about our Zongzi:
# 米泡的时间不够长 下一次的话可能头一天给它泡上
Rice isn't well-soaked. Next time should start soaking one day ahead
# 然后再用来包 米没有完全发涨
before using. Rice isn't bloating, so
# 所以有一点硬
it's a little bit hard,
# 熟是熟了的
although well-cooked.
# 这个当真的抵饿安
This is really satisfying
# 嗯
En
# 好了 本期视频就到这里 拜拜
OK. That's all for this episode. Bye bye.
# 快到端午节了自己做点来吃
You can cook some for the upcoming Dragon Boat Festival
# 这一次做得不够好 下一次再继续改进
Next time can only improve if you fail the first time